# 哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 我四伯跟漆二娃再我舅公那边
My uncle and Qi Erwa were at my granduncle’s place
# 我们一起弄了一大盆鱼过来做腊鱼
And we fetched a big tub of carp together to make some cured fish
# 就是因为猪肉涨价
This is due to the price increase of pork
# 猪肉涨价吃不起 我们弄点腊鱼来吃
Pork is now too expensive, so we will make some cured fish to eat
# 猪肉涨价就吃腊鱼
Time to eat cured fish when the price of pork is increasing
# 现在板鸭竹鼠鸡这些就要便宜点撒
Now ducks, bamboo rats and chicken are indeed cheaper
# 比猪肉便宜得哪里去了
Way cheaper than pork
# 我们平时不做这些因为今年猪肉涨价嘛
We don’t usually make this dish but this year, we have no choice because of the price increase of pork
# 是吧
Is that correct?
# 嗯
Yes
# 鸡鸭鱼都来一点
Chicken, ducks and fish. We can have a bit of all of them
# 来嘛 我们开始杀鱼嘛
Come on, let’s prepare the fish
# 要得 好
No problems
# 好生点哈
Be careful
# 来漆二娃 我去炒盐巴去了
Come here and do this Qi Erwa. I’m going to roast the salt
# 现在差不多了火升起来了
Now the temperature is coming up
# 这里20条鱼大概40斤
Here we have 20 carps weighing about 40 jin (=20kg)
# 40斤的话我用个6-7斤盐吧
For 40 jin of fish, let’s put in 6 to 7 jin of salt
# 因为这个鱼做咸一点吧才不会变味
Fish must be made a little bit saltier to avoid spoilage
# 其实这个跟那个腊鸭腊竹鼠差不多的
It’s actually similar to cured ducks and bamboo rats
# 就是放盐进去炒
Just pour in the salt and roast
# 炒完了之后放香料
Add in some spices when it’s done
# 炒香
Bring up the aroma
# 最后涂抹在鱼上面
And lastly rub the mixture onto the fish
# 腌制过4-6天再拿出来给它挂起来
Hang them out after curing them for 4-6 days
# 喜欢烟熏的可以放点柏树丫熏一下
If you like the smoky flavour, you can always get some cypress branches and smoke the fish
# 四伯爷帮我烧哈火嘛
Would you mind helping me with the fire uncle?
# 好嘛
Sure
# 这个要搞咸一点哦
This has to be salty
# 嗯 把它整咸点
Of course, I’ll make it so
# 不整咸点（放不久）
If not salty enough, it won’t last long (before it goes bad)
# 3包6斤盐
3 packs totaling 6 jin of salt
# 抓一把这个花椒
A handful of Sichuan peppercorns
# 整麻点哦
Make it a bit more numbing?
# 可以
Why not
# 再放点干辣椒
Some dried chillies
# 放点八角
Star anises
# 还有那个沙姜
And some galangals
# 这个香料一下去（锅）就闻到香了噶
You can instantly smell the aroma as soon as the spices go inside
# 哎呀 四伯爷来拨哈嘛
Do you want to toss the wok uncle?
# 我拨不来
No thanks. I can’t do it
# 拨不转噶
Hard to toss it?
# 我只有慢慢给你翻一下
I can only stir it slowly for you like this
# 再翻几下
A few more times
# 好这个已经差不多了
Alright, this should be done
# 我拿过去等他凉
I’ll take it over there for it to cool down
# 凉了之后腌鱼
Then cure the fish afterwards
# 四伯爷
Uncle
# 盐巴冷得差不多了我倒进去了哦
The salt is cool enough. I’m going to pour the salt in
# 要的呀 要的呀 一哈到进去吗
Yeah let’s go. All at once?
# 哈嘛
Yep
# 哈看咸不咸哦
Will it be too salty?
# 不咸40斤鱼
It won’t be. There are 40 jin of fish in there
# 你翻哈多
Would you flip the fish?
# 一个一个的翻 不要急慢慢来
One by one, no rush here. Do it slowly
# 不要慌
Don’t panic
# 烫不烫
Is to too hot?
# 不烫
Not at all
# 这哈子不烫了
It’s not hot now
# 诶 不要乱来撒
Hey, don’t mess it around
# 好 好不乱来
OK, I won’t make it messy
# 还是要看到舒服那样子撒
It needs to look comforting
# 好 哪个敢在你面前乱来哦
All good. Who dares to mess things around in front of you?
# 开玩笑
It must be kidding
# 是不是
Is that right?
# 是啊
Yeah
# 哎呀 多吃点鱼今年子哈
Wow, we are eating more fish this year
# 好
Definitely
# 少吃肉多吃鱼
More fish but less meat
# 是啊肉好贵嘛
Yes, as the meat is so expensive
# 我们这里这个鲤鱼来8块钱1斤
The carp are sold at only 8 Yuan per jin
# 8块钱1斤
8 Yuan per jin
# 猪肉好多呀
Pork is so expensive in the meantime
# 猪肉20斤1斤又回升转来了又是26-27块钱1斤了
It was 20 Yuan per jin but now it goes back to 26-27
# 可能到过年又是30-32块钱1斤的肉
The price could increase to 30-32 when approaching the Chinese New Year
# 对呀
Indeed
# 1斤肉我们可以吃3斤鱼了
We can eat 3 jin of fish for the price of 1 jin of meat
# 现在目前这个状况
Given the current circumstances
# 好 要得咯
Excellent. It looks good
# 慢点哈
Take it slowly
# 要注意哈形象
Pay attention to plating
# 这排好看着该安逸嘛
The whole lot looks much better when arranged neatly
# 小心烫哦
Watch out for the heat
# 好
Nice
# 现在我们把它抹均匀了放几天
Now we have rubbed the fish evenly and they need to stay still for a few days
# 放3天吧3天之后再把它穿起来
Maybe just 3 days. We will hang them after 3 days
# 给它做个十字架这边架好
Make a cross here for those fish
# 然后再用那个绳子绑起来捆在那个地方
And then tie them up with some strings over there
# 凉得哪里啊 到时候再熏一下不
Where should I hang them? Are we going to smoke them as well?
# 熏就挂在上次哪里熏
Just smoke them there where we did it last time
# 再把它熏一下熏出香味放到过年吃
Smoke them until fragrant and save them for the Chinese New Year
# 要放在楼上下面耗子凶得很耗子跟猫
They must be hung upstairs. The rats and cats downstairs are so destructive
# 哎呀 你看我整的些鸭子拿给那些猫耗子整（咬）了好多哦
Sigh. You know last time I did this, some of my ducks were bitten by those cats and rats
# 腿腿都那给它咬去了
Legs were all bitten off
# 我都没享受它还先享受
They enjoyed the ducks even before I did
# 它还先吃
They ate first
# 是啊
Yep
# 但是这个整得这么咸它下得了嘴噶
But this time, the fish are probably too salty for them to eat
# 嗨呀 它下得到嘴哦
No way, how can they can eat that?
# 你看嘛这样跟放盘子一样盘起盘起的多受看多美观撒
Look, just stack them like plates. They look so good
# 乱七八糟的放起形象都没得
If you mess up, they won't look good at all
# 形象不佳
Bad plating
# 看一下我们的杰作
Behold our masterpiece
# 该好看撒跟美女一样
It should look as good as beautiful girls
# 你看可以吧
Are you happy with it?
# 可以咯可以咯
Yes, it’s very good
# 要得 走嘛我们抬回去
Great. Let’s carry them back
# 好 拜拜
OK, bye bye
# 还没有说拜拜你都晓得要拜拜咯
We are not saying goodbye yet and you knew we were finishing?
# 那不是咋子安
Or what
# 来嘛 四伯爷抬哈
Come on uncle, give me a hand
# 好 拜拜
Cool, bye bye
# 拜拜
Bye bye